[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's a sutta, Samyuttanika 20.4, called Pots of Food.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, because if someone were to give away a hundred pots of food as a charity in the morning, a hundred pots of food as a charity at noon, and a hundred pots of food as a charity in the evening, and if someone else were to develop a mind of friendliness, even for a time it takes to pull a cow's udder, either in the morning, at noon, or in the evening, this would be more fruitful than the former.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, because you should train yourself thus, we will develop and cultivate the liberation of mind by friendliness, make it a vehicle, make it a basis, stabilize it, exercise ourselves in it, and fully perfect it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you should train yourselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this refers to the practice of metta, or how it's often translated as loving-kindness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's really about the mind of friendliness that is sustained regardless of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the first thing that a person will realize is that, yeah, you can evoke an attitude of friendliness towards everyone, but it doesn't last.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or it lasts only relatively speaking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sooner or later, it's just... it will... it will kind of drift into that abstract thinking of... you keep repeating to yourself friendliness and friendliness, but practically speaking, your mind is very much not friendly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you deal with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you... how do you address that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the reason why the mind doesn't listen to you is because, as the Buddha said, it's not pliable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it hasn't been tamed enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: It hasn't been brought into your control, which means your sense restraint, guarding of the sense doors and your watchfulness has not been sufficiently developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you were to understand how to cultivate the attitude, even if you could quickly evoke an attitude of friendliness, let's say like that, it will not get established in your mind, because the mind is still not not tamed, not tamed to the extent necessary
[SPEAKER_00]: for those phenomena to take root, to take place, and then to to stay enduring there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh... so that's why we often mention, you know, regardless whether it's the metta practice or jhāna practice or whichever other forms of samādhi you want to practice, that all has to come, eh... after your mind has been tamed and brought into, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, into like a good degree of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, that the mind needs to start to listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whereby then, when you think the thoughts of friendliness, the mind will become the mind of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you can think the thoughts of friendliness, but that's just...
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, trying to layer over a mind that is very unfriendly, or certainly, even if you make all the effort and constantly sort of dwell on thoughts of friendliness and thoughts of kindness, the mind kind of becomes indifferent towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason for that is, eh... the mind has not been sufficiently developed on its own, has not been sufficiently tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, eh... you are still more influenced by your mind than your mind is influenced by you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why all these contemplations that the Buddha encourages monks to do, pretty much apply to people that have already contained their mind in that right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind of friendliness, say, you say somebody has tamed their mind sufficiently enough, they don't need, they wouldn't need many specific instructions on how to do, how to do metta.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because, again, just a thought of friendliness for a well-trained mind, mind that has been reined in,
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind that obeys you and listens to you, mind that doesn't drift into sensuality, you know, in a split second, it doesn't fall into your will in a split second, all you need to do then is just
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember a friendly attitude, regardless of the person, regardless of the specific man or a woman you were friendly to, and just take the phenomenon of friendliness and dwell on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the mind will then direct, or rather, the mind will then follow that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: and it will be friendly towards anything and anyone, even people that are hostile.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that he would not perceive the hostility or bad behavior or foolish people around, but he will not have ill will towards them, because the the direction of ill will is directly opposite of the direction of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, given that the mind that listens to you has already traveled far enough in the direction of friendliness, even when it faces something that's not really nice, a person or something like that,
[SPEAKER_00]: It will take a lot more effort to, you know, go back now from that direction of friendliness into the direction of ill-will and then have the ill-will developed, than to just stay there and not change its framework of friendliness, regardless of the of the behavior of that person.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the... that's how you truly practice metta, and that's why Buddha said, yeah, it will lead to complete liberation of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you sustain it, the presence of that attitude of friendliness is completely, as I said, incompatible with the attitude of ill-will, attitude of craving, acting out of your desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if friendliness is sustained, passion will diminish.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you don't... you shouldn't be trying to practice this until you develop your mind, so that mind obeys you and listens to you and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do need to be aware that there is a certain order of things, how you develop them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can try and keep making effort to practice metta,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you're not sustaining it, if the mind is not quite, you know, as friendly as it should be, and if that framework of friendliness is not present throughout the day, it's not because metta is wrong or that meditation is not for you or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because the mind has not been tamed enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not mutually exclusive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like I will not do metta until I tame my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you can you can keep taming your mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: Anki practicing method, which will kind of at the same time serve as a criteria of how tamed your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're not trying to to to to direct your mind in like, for example, in this example, in the direction of friendliness, well, you will not see how much it disobeys you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you you do try to practice this and then see if the mind disobeys you, which means, okay, so review start things from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So is your is your virtue, you know, up to the
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to the task, has it been purified enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you seeing the danger in the slightest fault?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are your precepts intact?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you watchful generally of your intentions, you know, and whereby, you know, you're choosing things out of desire, boredom, or ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if so, if you recognize that there are blemishes there, how do you say?
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, you correct it there, in that regard, and then keep
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to develop the attitude of friendliness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if that taming of the mind is done, or when it is done properly, the attitude of friendliness will be much easier to establish and it will last much longer on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can use that, like you can use the
[SPEAKER_00]: attempts at trying to to practice friendliness correctly, you can use that pretty much as a as a kind of a measure of how much more your mind needs to be tamed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, eventually, when there is no effort required for you to sustain the attitude of friendliness,
[SPEAKER_00]: Regardless, as I said, of the circumstances, you know, okay, so the mind now is quite pliable and and it listens to me and then you can choose other ways of developing your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could start pondering on on the first jhāna or or any other types of
[SPEAKER_00]: Composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now the mind will be much more obedient.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all those subtle phenomenons of these practices that would result in complete liberation, the mind would become much more apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: much more palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and you can also just use the similar... you can extrapolate this principle and apply it to anything you read in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if things are not understood, or if they seem too abstract, or too sort of far-fetched,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's because the mind is not quite on the level where you can understand those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind has not been tamed enough, has not been withdrawn from centrality enough, has not been acting... has not been abstaining from acting out of desire long enough, and that's why these things are just abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just these distant ideas that you don't even see any basis for application in this experience here and now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all that can change if the mind, taming, is gradually developed and sustained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's kind of the necessary order of things.